Emma Elizabeth Walker Papers, 1899-1954
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Emma Elizabeth Walker Papers
1899-1954
Walker, Emma Elizabeth, 1864-
MS 169
1 box (1.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Physician; Children's author; Anti-suffragist; Birth control advocate; and Public health advocate. Papers consist primarily of Walker's writings and lectures, but also contain small amounts of biographical material and correspondence; plus information on women's health, the social and moral hygiene movements, turn-of-the-century childrearing practices, birth control and sexuality.
Biographical Note
Emma Elizabeth Walker was born in Springfield, Massachusetts, July 18, 1864. She grew up in Parkersburg, WV, received her A.B. from Smith College in 1887, and earned an M.D. from Johns Hopkins University in 1898. Later that year she opened her medical practice in New York City. For many years she was a clinical assistant surgeon in New York's Hospital for the Ruptured and Crippled. She authored Beauty Through Hygiene (1905), "Pretty Girl Questions" in Ladies Home Journal, and many articles and pamphlets for both popular and medical audiences. She lectured widely on the topics of personal and social hygiene and was a member of numerous medical and professional organizations.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Emma Elizabeth Walker Papers document her professional life. They consist primarily of Walker's writings and lectures, but also contain small amounts of biographical material and correspondence. In addition to documenting the work of a woman doctor at the turn of the century, the collection contains material relevant to women's health, the social and moral hygiene movements, turn-of-the-century childrearing practices, birth control and sexuality.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
The papers were donated by Emma Elizabeth Walker from 1942 to 1954.
Search Terms
Walker, Emma Elizabeth, 1864-; Blennerhassett Island (W. Va)--History--Sources; Public health--History--Sources; Women authors, American --20th century--Sources; Women--Health and hygiene--History--Sources; Women physicians--United States--History--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Additional papers of Emma Elizabeth Walker are at the Library of the New York Academy of Medicine. Associated material located in the Smith College Archives.
- Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Biographical: clippings and curriculum vitae, 1901-1918 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
- Correspondence, 1904-48 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Lecture programs, 1903, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- License to practice medicine, NY County, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  [See also Flat file]
- Medical records, degrees, awards, society memberships, etc., 1897-1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Reviews and announcements, 1901-11 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Writings
  - Ladies Home Journal "inserts", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ladies Home Journal articles, 1903-16 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Pamphlets on medical subjects, 1906, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Magazine articles, 1887-1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "F.A. Camping Party on Blennerhassett Island", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Blennerhassett Island (Parkerstown, WV) and Marietta, OH: articles, pamphlets, pictures, etc., 1899, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Lectures on social hygiene (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Society memberships (not medical), 1941-44, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Oversize Materials
  - Physician's license, 1899 (Map-case Flat File)
  - Smith College diploma, 1887 (Map-case Flat File)
  - Johns Hopkins diploma, 1898 (Map-case Flat File)
  - Medical Society of New York Certificate of Membership, 1904 (Map-case Flat File)